Now we're going to move the Player game object.
これから Player ゲームオブジェクトを動かしてみます
First let's think through how we
まず、Player ゲームオブジェクトに
want this Player game object to behave.
どんなふるまいが必要か考えてみましょう
We want to have the player fly around the game area,
Player はゲームエリアを飛び回り
stay on the play field and
プレイフィールド内にとどまり
not fly off in to space.
空間に飛び出すべきではありません。
We want to be able to collide with our collectable
アイテムのゲームオブジェクトと接触して
game objects and pick them up when we do this.
それを取得することも必要です
This requires physics.
これには 物理演算が必要です
Unity has two physics systems.
Unity には 2 種類の物理演算があります
One for 2D and one for 3D.
2D と 3D 用です
These systems are comparable to each other
これらのシステムは互いに匹敵し
and compatible with each other in that
互換性があります。 そのため
they can both be in the same scene
両方を同じシーンに設定することができます
but importantly they will
ただし、重要なのは
not interact with each other.
これらは相互に作用することはできません
For this project we'll be using
このプロジェクトには
2D physics.
2D 物理演算を利用します
To use 2D physics the game object
2D 物理演算を使用するには、ゲームオブジェクトに
needs to have a Rigidbody2d component attached.
Rigidbody2D コンポーネントをアタッチする必要があります
To attach a new component we must
新規のコンポーネントをアタッチするには
first select the game object we want to
最初に、そのコンポーネントをアタッチしたい
attach the component to,
ゲームオブジェクトを選びます
in this case we'll select our Player game object.
この場合は Player ゲームオブジェクトを選択します
Then we can either choose the
それから Component メニューで
Component menu and select
Physics 2D > Rigidbody2d
Physics 2D - Rigidbody2d
と選び
which would attach this component to the
このコンポーネントと選択したゲームオブジェクトを
game object we've selected.
アタッチするか
Or use the Add Component button
または、Inspector の Add Component ボタンを使い
in the inspector, choosing Rigidbody2d.
Rigidbody2D を選びます
It's important to be sure that we're adding
大切なのは、Physics や 3D でなく
the physics 2D version of this component
このコンポーネントの Physics 2D バージョンを
not the physics, or 3D version
選ぶことです
since we can choose between both the Rigidbody
なぜなら 3D Physics のRigidbody　も
component for 3D physics
Rigidbody2D　コンポーネントも
and the Rigidbody2d component.
どちらでも選べるからです
These component cannot work
これらのコンポーネントは一緒には使えません
together so be sure to choose the correct
作成中のゲームのタイプに
components for our game type.
正しいコンポーネントを選ぶよう気を付けてください
If we choose to we can rearrange
必要があれば
the order of the components on the game object
コンポーネントの右上の歯車型メニューで
using the context sensitive gear menu
ゲームオブジェクトのコンポーネントの順序を
in the upper-right of the component.
アレンジしなおすことができます
Doing this has no effect on the performance of our game,
これによって、ゲームのパフォーマンスに影響はありませんが
however having a consistent order
ゲームオブジェクトのコンポーネントの順番に
to the components on our game object
一貫性を持たせることは
may help us speed up our development
Project や Hierarchy を整理整頓した状態に
by keeping or maintaining an
維持することにより
organised project and hierarchy.
開発をスピードアップする助けになることもあります
Don't forget we can collapse
Component のタイトルバーをクリックして
or expand the component view
Component ビューを畳んだり広げたりできることを
by linking on the component's title bar
覚えておいてください
Now we need to get the player object
それでは、Player オブジェクトを制御して
moving under our control.
動かしてみることにしましょう
To do this we need to get input
オブジェクトを動かすには キーボードを通して
from our player through the keyboard and we
プレイヤーからの入力を取得し
need to apply that input to the Player game object
その入力を、シーン内で Player オブジェクトを動かす力として
as forces to move
as forces to move
the Player object in the scene.
適用する必要があります
We'll do this by using a script
これをPlayer ゲームオブジェクトに
that we attach to the Player game object.
スクリプトをアタッチして行います
Let's create a new C# script.
まず 新しいC# スクリプトを作成しましょう
To create a new script
新しいスクリプトを作るには
we have some choices.
いくつか方法があります
We can choose Assets - Create
Assets > Create > C# Script の順に選んで
to create our new C# script.
新しいC# スクリプトを作成するか
Or we can use the Create menu
または、Project ビューの Create メニューを
in the project view.
使用する方法もあります
But what might be more efficient in this
しかし、この場合 もっと効果的な方法は
case would be to select the Player game object
Player ゲームオブジェクトを選び
and use the Add Component button in the inspector.
Inspector の Add Component ボタンを使用します
The Add Component menu contains
Add Component メニューに
the selection New Script.
New Script という選択肢があります
This allows us to both create
これを選ぶと いっぺんに
and attach a script in one step.
スクリプトの作成とアタッチができます
First let's name this script
まずこのスクリプトを
PlayerController.
PlayerController と名付けます
We can choose the language of the script,
スクリプトの言語を選べます
which will be C#,
ここではC# を選び
and then click on Create and Add.
それから Create and Add をクリックします
Or simply hit the return or enter key
単に Return/Enter キーを押しても
to confirm our selection.
同様です
Unity will create, compile
Unity はこのスクリプトを作成、コンパイルし
and attach this script
選択したゲームオブジェクトに
to the selected game object.
アタッチします
We should note that this way of
気を付けたいのは
creating a script will create that
この方法でスクリプトを作成すると
script asset on the root
ルートか Project ビューの最上位に
or top level of our project view.
スクリプトアセットは作成されます
We'll need to move the asset in to the
Project ビューを効率的に保つために
Scripts directory in order to
そのアセットを Scripts ディレクトリに
maintain an organised project view.
移動します
If we select the script in our project view
Project ビューでスクリプトを選ぶと
we see a preview of the script asset
Inspector 内でスクリプトアセットの
in the inspector but this
プレビューが表示されます
text is not editable.
ただし、これは編集できません
Let's open the script for editing.
スクリプトを開いて編集してみましょう
We can do this in a number of ways.
たくさんの方法があります
When we're inspecting a game object
スクリプトがアタッチしたゲームオブジェクトを
with the script attached we can
検証しているときは
use the context sensitive gear menu.
歯車型メニューで Edit Script を選びます
We can double click on the script asset in
Project ビューでスクリプトアセットを
the project view, or we can use the
ダブルクリックします
Open button in the inspector
または、Project ビューで
when we have the script selected
スクリプトが選択されているときは
in our project view.
Inspector の Open ボタンを使います
This will open our script
こうして スクリプトを
in our preferred script editor.
好みのスクリプトエディターで開きます
First let's remove the sample
最初に、基本スクリプトの
code provided in the base script.
サンプルコードを削除します
Next let's think,
次に、このスクリプトで何をしたいのかを
what do we want to do with this script?
考えてみましょう
We want to check every frame
必用なのは、各フレームごとに
for player input, and then we
プレイヤーの入力をチェックして
want to apply that input to the
その入力を各フレームの動きとして
Player game object every frame as movement.
Player ゲームオブジェクトに適用することです
Where will we check for and apply this input?
では、どうやってこの入力をチェックして適用しましょうか。
We have two choices;
2 つ方法があります
Update() and FixedUpdate().
Update() と FixedUpdate() です
Update is called before rendering a frame,
Update はフレームをレンダリングする前に呼び出されます
and this is where most of our game
たいてのゲームコードは
code will go.
これを使います
FixedUpdate on the other hand is called
一方、FixedUpdate は
just before performing any
物理演算が行われる寸前に
physics calculations
呼び出されます
and this is where our physics code will go.
私たちは、こちらを物理演算コードに使います
We'll be moving our UFO by applying
力を Rigidbody2D に適用して
forces to the Rigidbody2d
UFO を動かします
meaning that this is physics.
つまり、物理演算です
The fact that it's 2D physics
2D 物理演算が
as distinct from 3D physics
3D のそれと違うことは
in this case is irrelevant.
この場合は、あまり関係ありません
We're going to put our code in FixedUpdate.
FixedUpdate にコードを加えることにします
The next question is what code are we going
次に、どのコードを
to want to put in FixedUpdate?
FixedUpdate に加えるかです
We know that we need input
Input (入力) が必要なことはわかっていますが
but how do we find out more?
それ以上どうやって調べたらよいでしょうか。
There's a shortcut in Monodevelop
MonoDevelop にはショートカットがあります
that searches the Unity API.
それで Unity API を検索できます
On the Mac it's Command + '
Mac では Command + '
and on Windows it's Control + '
Windows では Control + ' です
Select the item we want to research,
調べたいものを選びます
in our case Input,
この場合は Input です
and hold down the command or control key
そして、Command か Control キーを押しながら
and then press the ' key.
' キーを押します
This search brings up every reference
この検索で、Unity のドキュメンテーションにある
in our documentation related to Input.
Input に関する参照すべてが表示されます
Let's select Input at the top interface
一番上の Input を選んで
in to the Input system.
Input システムを見てみましょう
This brings up the page on Input.
これで Input に関するページが表示されます
This is the page on the Input class.
これは Input クラスのページです
We use this class to read the axis setup
このクラスは Input Manager で
in the Input Manager and to
軸の設定を読み込み、
access multitouch and accelerometer data
モバイルデバイスのmultitouch と accelerometer のデータに
on mobile devices.
アクセスするために使用されます
We read the text on the top of the page to
ページの上の方にあるテキストを読んで
understand how to use the class.
クラスの使用法を理解します
In our case to get Input from the
私たちの場合は、モバイルデバイスを含む
Player on all platforms, including mobile devices.
すべてのプラットフォームの Player から Input を取得します
Under the description is a
説明の下には
list of class variables and class functions.
クラスの変数と関数のリストがあります
The class variables how information
クラス変数は touchCount のように接触数、または
like the number of touches in touchCount,
gyro のようにデフォルトのジャイロスコープの参照などを
or a reference to the default gyroscope with gyro.
一時的に保持します
The class functions do something for us.
クラス関数は何かと役に立ちます
In our case we'll be using
ここでは
Input.GetAxis.
Input.GetAxis を使います
When we find the item we want
興味があるものをみつけたときは
we click on the link to bring up a page
リンクをクリックして、その関数や変数に関する
on the function or variable.
ページを開きます
Let's look at input.GetAxis.
input.GetAxis を見てみましょう
This page includes the signature of the function,
このページには関数のシグネチャと
a description of the function
関数の説明と
and code snippets showing
Unity の Java Script と C# で
us how to use it in Unity's
どのように使うかを示す
Java Script and C#.
コードスニペッツが含まれています
We will be using C#.
ここではC# を使います
For more information on Input and the Input Manager
Input と Input Manager に関する情報は
please see the information linked below.
下のリンクのページを参照してください
We'll be using Input.GetAxis
これから Input.GetAxis を
in a very similar way to the
表示されているコードスニペッツと
code snippet shown.
とても似た用法で使います
Let's return to our script
スクリプトに戻って
and write our code.
コードを書いてみましょう
Type float moveHorizontal = Input.GetAxis (*Horizontal*);
以下を入力します float moveHorizontal = Input.GetAxis (*Horizontal*);
float moveVertical = Input.GetAxis (*Vertical*);
float moveVertical = Input.GetAxis (*Vertical*);
Now we can delete the Input line.
そして Input の行を消します
This grabs the input from
これで キーボードを通して
our Player through the keyboard.
Player から入力を取得できます
The float variables moveHorizontal
Float 変数の moveHorizontal と
and moveVertical
moveVertical は
record the input from the horizontal
キーボードのキーによって制御される
and vertical axis which are controlled
水平と垂直の軸からの
by the keys on the keyboard.
入力を記録します
These keys are set by default
InputManager では、これらのキーはデフォルトで
in the InputManager.
設定されます
Our Player game object uses a
Player ゲームオブジェクトは
Rigidbody2d and
Rigidbody2D を利用して
interacts with the 2D physics engine.
2D 物理演算エンジンと交信します
We'll use this input to add
入力することにより
forces to the Rigidbody2dC
Rigidbody2D に力を加え
and move the Player game object in the scene.
シーンで Player ゲームオブジェクトを動かします
To know more about how to apply forces
どうやって Rigidbody2D に力を適用するかを
to the Rigidbody2d
もっと知るために
let's check the documentation.
ドキュメンテーションを見てみましょう
First type Rigidbody2d in to our script.
最初に スクリプトに Rigidbody2D と入力します
Now select Rigidbody2d and
Rigidbody2D を選んで
hold down the command key on the Mac
Mac なら Command キー
or the control key on Windows
Windows なら Control キー と
and type '
‘ を入力します
Again this brings us to a page
再び、検索用語 Rigidbody2D で検索される
with a search term Rigidbody2d.
ページが表示されます
Let's click on that.
それをクリックしてみましょう
This brings up the Rigidbody2d page.
Rigidbody2D ページが表示されます
If we want to apply force to our Player game object
Player ゲームオブジェクトに力を適用したければ
we need to do something,
何かをしなければなりません
so let's take a look at the functions
それで、Rigidbody2D クラスに使用可能な
available to the Rigidbody2d class.
関数を見てみましょう
We can read the descriptions until we
使いたい関数が見つかるまで
find the one we want.
説明を読んで探します
In this case let's choose AddForce.
今回はAddForce を選びましょう
This adds force to the Rigidbody2d.
これで Rigidbody2D に力を加えます
As a result it will start moving.
結果として、動き始めます
Click the link and we go to the
リンクをクリックして
page on AddForce.
AddForce のページを開いてください
We can see the signature of the function
ページの一番上に
at the top of the page.
関数のシグネチャがあります
The signature tells us
シグネチャによると、Rigidbody2D に力を加えるには
we need a vector2
vector2 と
and an optional ForceMode
オプションで ForceMode　が
to add force to our Rigidbody2d.
必要です
What is a vector2?
Vector2 とは何でしょうか
For more detailed information on vector2
Vector2 に関する詳しい情報は
please see the information linked below.
下のリンクのページを参照してください
But in simple terms the vector2
簡単に言うと Vector2 は
holds two decimal values
2 つの十進法の値を
in one container.
1 つのコンテナーに保持します
This makes it easy for us to move around
これによって
and use values for things like a
2D スペースの力のような
force in 2D space
X と Y 両軸の力を必要とする値を
which requires a value for force
自由に変えて使用することが
on both the X and Y axis.
容易になります
All of our documentation pages are linked together.
すべてのドキュメンテーションページは関連付けられています
If we were to click on Vector2
Vector2 をクリックすると
we would be taken to the documentation
そのドキュメンテーションが
page for Vector2.
開きます
The next concept that we need to cover is
次に解決すべき問題は
how to get a hold of,
ゲームオブジェクトの異なるコンポーネントを
or how to reference different
どのように捕らえて
components on our game object.
参照するかということです
We're currently writing a script called
私たちは現在、PlayerController という
PlayerController, which is attached
スクリプトを作成しています
as a script component
それはスクリプトコンポーネントとして
to our Player game object.
Player ゲームオブジェクトにアタッチされています
From this script we need to add force
このスクリプトで Rigidbody2D コンポーネントを使って
using the Rigidbody2d component.
力を加えます
We want to access that component
スクリプトを通してそのコンポーネントに
from this script.
アクセスする必要があります
There are several ways we can do this,
何種類か方法がありますが
but in our case we'll cover only one
同じゲーム上の他のコンポーネントに
of the main ways of accessing
アクセスする主な方法のうち
another component on the same game object.
ここでは　1 つだけを取り上げます
We'll create a variable to hold
スクリプト内で
this reference in our script
この参照を記憶する変数を作り
and we'll set this reference in the Start function.
この参照を Start 関数に設定します
Let's return to our script.
スクリプトに戻りましょう
In our script we need to write
スクリプトに以下を入力します
Private Rigidbody2D rb2d
Private Rigidbody2D rb2d
to create the variable to hold the reference.
これは、参照を記憶する変数を作成します
We're going to declare a new Start function
新しい Start 関数を宣言し
and in it we're going to write
そこに以下を入力します
rb2d = GetComponent ();
rb2d = GetComponent ();
In FixedUpdate let's use
FixedUpdate 内で
Rigidbody2d.AddForce with a vector2
Vector2 の値を持つ Rigidbody2d.AddForce を
and we'll leave the ForceMode at
ForceMode をデフォルト設定で
default by omitting it from our code
使用します
So in our script we need to type
そして、スクリプトに
rb2d.AddForce and then some vector2 value.
rb2d.AddForce といくつかの Vector2 の値が必要です
Now how do we get our two float values
さて、どうやって 2 つの float の値を
in to a vector2 value?
Vector2 に入力したらよいでしょうか。
Let's create a new vector2
まず、新しいVector2 変数を作り
variable called Movement.
Movement と呼ぶことにします
This will be equal to a new vector2
これは X と Y の値で構成される
that's made up of an X and a Y.
新しい Vector2 とイコールで結ばれています
The X and Y values will determine
X と Y の値によって
the direction of the force
UFO に加える
we will add to our UFO.
力の方向が決まります
What is our X value?
ここで X 値は何を指すでしょうか
That would be moveHorizontal.
moveHorizontal です
With this our left and right keys will
これを使って、左と右のキーは
add force moving the UFO to the left or right.
UFO を左か右に動かす力を加えます
What is our Y?
ここで Y 値は何を指すでしょうか
That would be moveVertical.
moveVertical　です
Now we use movement,
rb2d.AddForce の
our new vector2 value in rb2d.AddForce
新しい Vector2 の値 movement を使って
as rb2d.AddForce(movement)
rb2d.AddForce(movement)　とします
Let's save this script and return to Unity.
スクリプトを保存して Unity に戻ります
We can check for errors in our footer
フッターかコンソールでエラーを確認できます
or the console, and there are none.
エラーはありません
Good.
OK です
Now let's test what we've written.
さて、スクリプトをテストしてみましょう
Hit Play.
再生ボタンを押してください
The first thing we'll notice is that the Player
初めに気づくのはPlayer がすぐに
immediately flies downward off the playing field.
プレイフィールドを外れて、下まで飛んでいってしまうことです
This is because the default for our Rigidbody2D
これは、Rigidbody2D のデフォルトで
is to apply gravity downwards
Y 軸にそって下向きに重力が
along the Y axis.
適用されるためです
Since our game is designed as a
このゲームはトップダウンビューで
top-down view this doesn't make any sense.
デザインされているので適切でありません
Exit Play mode.
Play モードを閉めます
To illuminate this behaviour we'll
このビヘイビアを取り除くために
set the Gravity Scale property
Player にアタッチしている Rigidbody2D の
of our Rigidbody2d attached to our Player
Gravity Scale プロパティーを
to 0.
0 に設定します
This means that no gravity
つまり、重力の影響をを
will be applied.
無しにします
This is one reason why making a top-down
これが、トップダウン 2D ゲームを作るのが
2D game is a little easier,
少し簡単である理由の 1 つです
because we don't have to deal with gravity in our physics.
物理演算で重力を考えなくてよいからです
Now play again and test.
では、もう 1 度プレイしてテストしましょう
By using the keys setup in the InputManager
InputManager で設定したキーを使って
the UFO moves in the scene.
UFO はシーン内で動きます
Gravity is now off, but the player
重力はオフですが、プレイヤーの動きは
is still very slow.
まだ、かなり遅いです
This is probably too slow to be playable
プレイするには多分遅すぎます
but the basic concept works 100%.
ただし、基本コンセプトは完璧です
To stop testing exit Play mode.
テストを終わらせるには Play モードを終了します
Let's return to our code and create a
コードに戻り、
tool that will give us control over
UFO のスピードを制御する
the speed of the UFO.
ツールを作りましょう
We need to multiply our movement
ある値で movement を乗ずる
by some value.
必要があります
We could simply enter that value here
その値は、単純にスクリプトに加えることもできますが
on our script, but if we ever needed to make any
ただし、調整や変更が
tweaks or changes we would have
必要になった場合は
to return to our scripting editor
スクリプトエディターに戻り
and change the value in the script,
スクリプトの値を変更し
and then recompile.
リコンパイルしなくてはなりません
This would take time.
これでは時間がかかります
The solution is to create a public
解決策として、スクリプトに
variable in our script.
パブリックの変数を作成します
Let's create a public float called Speed.
では、パブリックの float 型の Speed を作りましょう
By creating a public variable in our script
スクリプトにパブリックの変数を作ることで
this variable will show up in the inspector
この変数は編集可能なプロパティーとして
as an editable property.
Inspector に表示されます
When we use a public variable we can
パブリック変数を使うと
make all of our changes in the editor.
すべての変更をエディターで行えます
Let's now multiply movement by speed.
それでは、movement を　speed で乗じてみましょう
We can use this to control
この方法を使うと
our movement value from
エディターで
inside the editor.
movement の値を制御できます
Let's save these changes and return to Unity.
この変更を保存して Unity に戻ります
When we return to the editor we can see
エディターにもどると
our PlayerController script
PlayerController Script　に
now has a Speed property.
Speed プロパティーがあることに気づきます
Let's set this property to 1000.
このプロパティーを 1000 に設定しましょう
Play the scene and test.
シーンを再生しテストします
It works, but the Player is moving
動きますが、プレイヤーの動きが
way too fast!
速すぎますね。
But changes are fast too.
でも、変更も素早くできますよ
Let's exit Play mode and let's
プレイモードを終了して
change the value to 10.
値を 10 に変えましょう
That's better!
良くなりました
Congratulations, we can now move our
よくできました。プレイヤーを
Player character.
動かせるようになりました
You'll notice however that the player can just
ただし、壁を通り抜けて飛ぶだけです
fly through the walls, which is not what we want.
これは、私たちの望んでいるものとは違います
In the next lesson we'll add collision detection.
次のレッスンでは、衝突の検出を加えます